Nelson W. Aldrich Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Nelson W. Aldrich Papers 1777-1930 (bulk 1879-1915)
MSS10389
Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth), 1841-1915
42,750 items 140 containers plus 3 oversize 58 linear feet 73 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
United States representative and senator from Rhode Island, financier, and philanthropist. Correspondence, journal, appointment books, drafts of speeches, memoranda, financial records, reports, legislative matter, scrapbooks, serial publications, and other printed material relating chiefly to Aldrich's career in Congress.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Aldrich, Abby Pearce Chapman, 1845-1917. Abby Pearce Chapman Aldrich diaries. 1904-1912.; Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth), 1841-1915.; Aldridge family.; Anthony, Henry B. (Henry Bowen), 1815-1884--Correspondence.; Camden, Johnson Newlon, 1828-1908--Correspondence.; Cannon, Henry White, 1850-1934--Correspondence.; Chace, Jonathan, 1829-1917--Correspondence.; Choate, Charles F. (Charles Francis), 1828-1911.; Crane, Winthrop Murray, 1853-1920--Correspondence.; Hale, Eugene, 1836-1918--Correspondence.; Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1850-1924--Correspondence.; Nichols, Jeannette Paddock, 1890- --Correspondence.; Nicholson, William Thomas, 1834-1893--Correspondence.; Rockefeller, John D., Jr. (John Davison), 1874-1960.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; Stephenson, Nathaniel W. (Nathaniel Wright), 1867-1935--Correspondence.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.; Whitman, William, 1842-1928--Correspondence.
Subjects
Tariff--United States.
Places
Rhode Island--Politics and government--1865-1950.
Titles
Hepburn Act, 1906.
Occupations
Financiers.; Philanthropists.; Representatives, U.S. Congress--Rhode Island.; Senators, U.S. Congress--Rhode Island.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Nelson W. Aldrich, United States representative and senator from Rhode Island, financier, and philanthropist, were given to the Library of Congress in four installments. The first was received in 1944 from Aldrich’s children, Winthrop W. Aldrich and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. John D. Rockefeller, Jr., donated additions to the collection in 1955 and 1956 from the papers of his late wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. The last installment was given by the Seminary of Our Lady of Providence, Rhode Island, in 1970.
Additional Guides
A note about the Nelson W. Aldrich papers appeared in the Library of Congress Information Bulletin 15 (Nov. 13 1956), and the material was described in the Quarterly Journal of the Library of Congress 13 (May 1956):152, and 14 (May 1957): 116. In 1973, the Library published Nelson W. Aldrich, a Register and Index of His Papers in the Library of Congress. The index is available as a PDF document.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Nelson W. Aldrich are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of these papers is available on 73 reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1841, Nov. 6 Born, Foster, R. I.
1862 Served with tenth Rhode Island Volunteers
1865 Became junior partner in Rhode Island wholesale grocery firm
1866 Married Abby Pearce Chapman (died 1917)
1869-1875 Member, Providence, R.I., common council (president, 1872-1873)
1875-1877 Member, Rhode Island state house of representatives (speaker of the house, 1876-1877)
1876 Delegate, Republican national convention
1879-1881 Member, U.S. House of Representatives
1881-1911 Member, U.S. Senate
1908-1912 Chairman, National Monetary Commission
1915, Apr. 16 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Nelson Wilmarth Aldrich (1841-1915) span the years 1777-1930, with the bulk of the material concentrated in 1879-1915. The collection is composed primarily of correspondence, printed matter, and material relating to tariff legislation and the National Monetary Commission, supplemented by diaries, notebooks, speeches, research notes, serial publications, financial records, and miscellaneous items.
The collection focuses on Aldrich’s service as United States Senator from Rhode Island, 1881-1911 and reflects his involvement with national economic and fiscal policy. Tariff legislation is a recurring theme throughout the Correspondence series, particularly during the years of major tariff revision in 1890, 1897, and 1909. The correspondence, mainly incoming mail from businessmen representing a wide range of economic interests, reveals the depth of feeling generated by the prospect of tariff revision and the importance of the issue during these years. The letters also provide an insight into American business practices and the economic views of a large segment of the American business community during this era of industrial expansion. Aldrich’s personal attention to the details of rate revision is revealed in the tariff file, while his speeches help document his attitude toward tariff duties as a source of protection for American industry from foreign competition.
Aldrich gave considerable attention during his last years in office to the problems of United States monetary policy. Following the Panic of 1907, with its accompanying rash of bank failures, he cosponsored the Aldrich-Vreeland Act of 1908, providing for the establishment of a National Monetary Commission to study banking and currency operations at home and abroad and to suggest changes in American practices.
The National Monetary Commission’s correspondence for the years 1908-1912 documents its activities and Aldrich’s role as chairman. Much of the commission’s correspondence was with bankers, public officials, financial experts, and academicians employed to prepare special studies, translate documents, and collect statistics on financial operations and monetary systems in foreign nations as well as in the United States. Aldrich and other members of the commissions visited England, France and Germany to consult with experts and collect data, and specialists representing the commission made similar visits to other nations and reported their findings. Hearings were held in selected American cities to solicit opinions from bankers and other interested parties, while numerous individuals sent unsolicited opinions and plans directly to the commission. Most of the letters were sent and received by Abram Piatt Andrew, special assistant to the commission; Arthur B. Shelton, secretary to the commission; and staff members Charles E. Alden, J. William Sheetz, and William A. Slade.
Aldrich’s personal views are reflected in occasional correspondence, speeches delivered to promote monetary reform, and in the final report of the commission soon labeled the “Aldrich Plan.” The commission’s correspondence is also a rich source of information regarding American financial institutions in the early twentieth century and the views of members of the financial community at the time. The National Monetary Commission file contains most of its publications as well as a sampling of the collected data and related material.
After the death of Senator Henry B. Anthony in 1884, Aldrich assumed Anthony’s former position as a powerful figure in Rhode Island politics. Letters in the collection from numerous state political figures, particularly Henry B. Gardner and Charles R. Bryaton, kept Aldrich abreast of local affairs and include requests for favors, advice, and patronage.
Aldrich’s personal affairs and family relations form a relatively small portion of the collection. A series of letters written to his future wife in 1865-1866 offers a glimpse into his personal relations and plans at this time. Letters written to Mrs. Aldrich during his first trip abroad in 1872-1873 describe family relations and reveal his initial impressions of European society and culture. Scattered letters in the Correspondence series and the financial records offer insight into his extensive financial ventures, particularly his investments in the rubber industry.
Principal correspondents include William B. Allison, Henry B. Anthony, Jonathan Bourne (1811-1889), C. R. Brayton, Jonathan Chace, William E. Chandler, Charles A. Conant, Henry Pomeroy Davison, Eugene Hale, Philander C. Knox, Charles Warren Lippitt, Stephen B. Luce, Orville Hitchock Platt, Theodore Roosevelt (1858-1919), William H. Taft, Henry Moore Teller, Paul M. Warburg, and George Peabody Wetmore.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in ten series:
Diaries and Notebooks, 1863-1927
General Correspondence, 1777-1915
Tariff, circa 1880-circa 1915
National Monetary Commission, 1908-1912
Biographer’s Papers, circa 1860-circa 1930
Financial Records, circa 1880-circa 1915
Speech File, 1881-1913
Serial Publications, circa 1885-circa 1915
Printed Matter, circa 1880-circa 1915
Miscellany, circa 1862-circa 1915
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm78010389
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 15,443
- Diaries and Notebooks, 1863-1927 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  Diaries and social engagement books of Abby Pearce Chapman Aldrich, bound and unbound shorthand letters and notes of Nelson W. Aldrich, a Civil War company roll book, a fraternal lodge address book, minutes of the Senate Finance Committee for Dec. 1863 to June 1864, and a journal relating to the Hepburn Act of 1906.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Aldrich, Abby Pearce Chapman (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Diaries, Jan. 1904; Jan.-May 1912 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Engagement books, 1905-1910 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Hepburn Act journal, no author, 1927 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Civil War roll book, 1863 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Fraternal lodge address book, undated (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Senate Finance Committee minutes, Dec. 1863-June 1864 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Bound shorthand letters, circa Dec. 1882-Jan. 1884 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Bound shorthand notes, undated (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Unbound shorthand letters, circa 1882-1909, undated (Box 1, Reel 1)
- General Correspondence, 1777-1915 (Box 2-65, Reel 2-48)
  Mainly letters received and occasional letters sent by Aldrich, and letters sent and received by staff members of the National Monetary Commission.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1777 (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - 1846-Nov. 1879 (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - Dec. 1879, Dec.-May 1880 (Box 3, Reel 3)
  - June 1880-Jan. 1881 (Box 4, Reel 3)
  - Feb.-Dec. 1881 and 1881, no day or month (Box 5, Reel 4)
  - Jan.-Mar. 1882 (Box 6, Reel 5)
  - Apr.-June 1882 (Box 7, Reel 6-7)
  - 1-14 July 1882 (Box 8, Reel 7)
  - 15 Dec. 1882-19 Jan. 1883 (Box 9, Reel 7-8)
  - Jan. 20-Feb. 28 1883 (Box 10, Reel 8)
  - Mar.-Aug. 1883 (Box 11, Reel 8-9)
  - 1 Sept.-26 Dec. 1883 (Box 12, Reel 9-10)
  - 27 Dec. 27 1883-29 Feb.1884 (Box 13, Reel 10)
  - 1 Mar.-25 Apr. 1884 (Box 14, Reel 11)
  - 26 Apr.-30 June 1884 (Box 15, Reel 11-12)
  - July-Oct. 1884 (Box 16, Reel 12)
  - 1 Nov. 1884-21 Jan. 1885 (Box 17, Reel 13)
  - 22 Jan.-28 Feb. 1885 (Box 18, Reel 13-14)
  - Mar.-July 1885 (Box 19, Reel 14-15)
  - Aug.-Dec. 1885 and 1885, no day or month (Box 20, Reel 15)
  - Jan.-Feb. 1886 (Box 21, Reel 15-16)
  - Mar.-Apr. 1886 (Box 22, Reel 16-17)
  - May-June 1886 (Box 23, Reel 17-18)
  - July-Dec. 1886 and 1886, no day or month (Box 24, Reel 18)
  - July-Dec. 1886 and 1886, no day or month (Box 25, Reel 18-19)
  - Jan.-Apr. 1889 (Box 26, Reel 19)
  - May-Sept. 1889 (Box 27, Reel 19-20)
  - Oct. 1889-Dec. 1890 and 1890, no day or month (Box 28, Reel 20)
  - Jan. 1891-July 1892 (Box 29, Reel 21)
  - Aug. 1892-June 1897 (Box 30, Reel 21)
  - July 1897-May 1899 (Box 31, Reel 22)
  - June 1899-Sept. 1900 (Box 32, Reel 22)
  - Oct. 1900-Apr. 1902 (Box 33, Reel 23)
  - May 1902-June 1903 (Box 34, Reel 23)
  - July 1903-Sept. 1905 (Box 35, Reel 24)
  - Oct. 1905-Dec. 1906 and 1906, no day or month (Box 36, Reel 24)
  - Jan. 1907-Jan. 1908 (Box 37, Reel 25)
  - Feb.-Apr. 1908 (Box 38, Reel 26)
  - May-Aug. 1908 (Box 39, Reel 27)
  - Sept.-Dec. 1908 and 1908, no day or month (Box 40, Reel 28)
  - 1 Jan.-8 Feb. 1909 (Box 41, Reel 29)
  - 9 Feb.-13 Mar. 1909 (Box 42, Reel 30)
  - 14-31 Mar. 1909 (Box 43, Reel 30)
  - 1-19 Apr. 1909 (Box 44, Reel 31)
  - 20 Apr.-12 May 1909 (Box 45, Reel 32)
  - 13 May-11 June 1909 (Box 46, Reel 33)
  - 13 May-11 June 1909 (Box 47, Reel 34)
  - 11 July-8 Aug. 1909 (Box 48, Reel 35)
  - 9 Aug.-22 Sept. 1909 (Box 49, Reel 36)
  - 23 Sept.-15 Nov. 1909 (Box 50, Reel 37)
  - 16 Nov.-23 Dec. 1909 (Box 51, Reel 38)
  - 24 Dec. 1909-31 Jan. 1910 (Box 52, Reel 39)
  - 1 Feb.-17 Mar. 1910 (Box 53, Reel 40)
  - 18 Mar.-30 Apr. 1910 (Box 54, Reel 41)
  - May-June 1910 (Box 55, Reel 42)
  - July-Sept. 1910 (Box 56, Reel 42)
  - 1 Oct.-15 Dec. 1910 (Box 57, Reel 43)
  - 16 Dec. 1910-24 Feb. 1911 (Box 58, Reel 44)
  - 25 Feb.-31 May 1911 (Box 59, Reel 45)
  - June-Sept. 1911 (Box 60, Reel 45)
  - 1 Oct.-13 Dec. 1911 (Box 61, Reel 46)
  - 14 Dec. 1911-30 Apr. 1912 (Box 62, Reel 47)
  - May 1912-Feb. 1914 (Box 63, Reel 47)
  - Mar.-Dec. 1914 and 1914, no day or month (Box 64, Reel 48)
  - Jan.-June 1915, undated (Box 65, Reel 48)
- Tariffs, circa 1880-circa 1915 (Box 66-74, Reel 49-54)
  Bills, amendments, schedules, petitions, resolutions, reports, statements, and miscellaneous items relating to tariff rates and tariff legislation.
  - Bills, amendments, and schedules (Box 66-70, Reel 49-52)
  - Miscellaneous schedules, petitions, statements, statistics, reports, memoranda, resolutions, and fragments relating to the tariff (Box 71-74, Reel 53-54)
- National Monetary Commission, 1908-1912 (Box 75-84, Reel 55-58)
  Publications, miscellaneous draft reports, proceedings, statements, statistics, and papers relating to the National Monetary Commission.
  - Publications Only title pages are available on microfilm edition (Box 75-78, Reel 55)
  - Miscellaneous reports, statements, minutes, lists, memoranda, questionnaires, printed matter, and fragments relating to the work of the commission (Box 79-84, Reel 55-58)
- Biographer's Papers, circa 1860-circa 1930 (Box 85-91, Reel 58-61)
  Research notes collected by Jeannette Paddock Nichols and Nathaniel W. Stephenson for the latter’s biography, Nelson W. Aldrich, a Leader in American Politics (1930), supplemented by related correspondence and a few miscellaneous items.
  Arranged by type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1924-1930, undated (Box 85, Reel 58)
  - General outline (Box 85, Reel 58)
  - Interviews, memoranda, and miscellaneous (Box 85, Reel 58)
  - Notes (Box 85, Reel 58)
    - circa 1860-1886 (Box 85, Reel 58)
    - 1887-1893 (Box 86, Reel 59)
    - 1894-1901 (Box 87, Reel 59-60)
    - 1902-1905 (Box 88, Reel 60)
    - 1902-1905 (Box 89, Reel 60)
    - 1906-1909 (Box 90, Reel 61)
    - 1910-1915 (Box 91, Reel 61)
- Financial Records, circa 1880-circa 1915 (Box 92-100)
  Checkbooks, checks, statements, bills, receipts, vouchers, occasional correspondence, and miscellaneous items relating to Aldrich’s personal financial affairs and to the financial transactions of the National Monetary Commission.
  - Checkbooks (Box 92)
  - Checks (Box 93-94)
  - Checks and statements (Box 95)
  - Miscellaneous bills, receipts, vouchers, statements, and occasional correspondence relating to Aldrich’s personal financial affairs and the financial transactions of the National Monetary Commission (Box 96-100)
- Speech File, 1881-1913 (Box 101-106, Reel 62-64)
  Holograph, typed and printed speeches by Aldrich, including drafts and related research material.
  Arranged chronologically and by type of material.
  - 1881-1890 (Box 101, Reel 62)
  - 1891-Nov. 1909 (Box 102, Reel 62)
  - Nov. 1909-Oct. 1911 (Box 103, Reel 63)
  - Nov. 1911-Oct. 1913 (Box 104, Reel 63-64)
  - Notes for tariff speeches
  - Notes for monetary speeches (Box 105, Reel 64)
  - Undated and fragmentary
  - Undated and fragmentary (Box 106, Reel 64)
- Serial Publications, circa 1885-circa 1915 (Box 107-114, Reel 65)
  Issues of serial publications and miscellaneous journals.
  Arranged by title and therein chronologically.
  - Bankers Magazine (Box 107, Reel 65)
    - 1887-1888 (Box 107, Reel 65)
    - 1908 (Box 107, Reel 65)
    - 1910 (Box 107, Reel 65)
    - 1911-1913 (Box 108, Reel 65)
  - Quarterly Publications of the American Statistical Association, 1899-1905, 1912 (Box 108, Reel 65)
  - Protectionist (Box 109, Reel 65)
    - 1902-1914, 1908-1913 (Box 109, Reel 65)
    - 1914-1915 (Box 110, Reel 65)
  - Journal of the American Bankers Association (Box 110, Reel 65)
    - 1908-1910 (Box 110, Reel 65)
    - 1911-1912 (Box 111, Reel 65)
  - Bradstreet’s Book of Commercial Ratings.... (Box 111, Reel 65)
    - 1885-1886 (Box 111, Reel 65)
    - 1886-1887 (Box 112, Reel 65)
    - 1891-1894 (Box 112, Reel 65)
    - 1896 (Box 112, Reel 65)
    - 1898-1899 (Box 112, Reel 65)
  - Miscellaneous journals (Box 113-114, Reel 65)
- Printed Matter, circa 1880-circa 1915 (Box 115-129, Reel 65-67)
  Government documents and bound and unbound printed matter.
  - Government documents (Box 115-120, Reel 65)
  - Bound printed matter (Box 121-126, Reel 65)
  - Unbound printed matter (Box 127-129, Reel 66-67)
- Miscellany, circa 1862-circa 1915 (Box 130-140, Reel 68-73)
  Bound facsimile letters, biographical information, material relating to Aldrich’s rubber investments, speeches, articles, memoranda, proceedings, legal briefs and cases, contracts, reports, requests for supplies, cards, tickets, scrapbooks of clippings relating primarily to tariff and banking matters, acknowledgments, invitations, loose clippings, photographs, and miscellaneous items.
  - Bound facsimiles, 1862-1863 (Box 130, Reel 68)
  - Biographical data (Box 130, Reel 68)
  - Rubber-business contracts, reports, and miscellany (Box 130, Reel 68)
  - Speeches and articles (Box 130, Reel 68)
    - 1879-1890 (Box 130, Reel 68)
    - 1891-1915, undated (Box 131, Reel 68-69)
  - Memoranda (Box 131, Reel 68-69)
  - Proceedings (Box 131, Reel 68-69)
  - Legal briefs and cases (Box 131, Reel 68-69)
  - Contracts (Box 132, Reel 68-69)
  - Reports (Box 132, Reel 68-69)
  - Requests for supplies (Box 132, Reel 68-69)
  - Cards and tickets (Box 132, Reel 68-69)
  - Scrapbooks of clippings mainly regarding tariffs (Box 133, Reel 68-69)
    - 1884-1886 (Box 133 (oversize), Reel 68-69)
    - 1885-1890 (Box 134 (oversize), Reel 70)
    - 1911 (Box 135 (oversize), Reel 70)
  - Acknowledgments (Box 136, Reel 70)
  - Invitations (Box 136, Reel 70)
  - Invitations (Box 137, Reel 70)
  - Clippings (Box 138-140, Reel 70-72)
  - Resolutions, certificates, lists, draft bills, fragments, and miscellaneous items (Box 141-143, Reel 72-73)